<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
  <book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
        xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
        xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
        xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	xml:id="cf-intro" 
        version="5.0">
    <?rax pdf.url="../../../cf-intro-latest.pdf"?>
  <title>Cloud Files™ Introduction</title>
  <info>
    <author>
      <personname>
        <firstname/>
        <surname/>
      </personname>
      <affiliation>
        <orgname>Rackspace Cloud</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
    <copyright>
        <year>2009</year>
        <year>2010</year>
        <year>2011</year>
        <year>2012</year>
       <year>2013</year>
        <holder>Rackspace US, Inc.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <releaseinfo>API v1</releaseinfo>
    <productname>Cloud Files™</productname>
    <pubdate/>
    <legalnotice role="rs-api">
        <annotation>
            <remark>Copyright details are filled in by the template.</remark>
        </annotation>
    </legalnotice>
    <abstract>
      <para> This document is intended for potential and actual users of Rackspace Cloud Files™ and
        for software developers interested in developing applications using the Rackspace Cloud
        Files™ Application Programming Interface (<abbrev>API</abbrev>). </para>
    </abstract>
    <raxm:metadata
	xmlns:raxm="http://docs.rackspace.com/api/metadata">
      <raxm:displayname>Getting Started Guide</raxm:displayname>
      <raxm:product version="v1">files</raxm:product>
      <raxm:priority>10</raxm:priority>
    </raxm:metadata>
  </info> 
  <chapter xml:id="Introduction-d1e82">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <info>
    <raxm:metadata xmlns:raxm="http://docs.rackspace.com/api/metadata">
      <raxm:type>concept</raxm:type>
      <raxm:product version="v1">files</raxm:product> 
      <raxm:priority>0</raxm:priority>
    </raxm:metadata>
    </info>
    <para>
      Rackspace Cloud Files™ is an affordable, redundant, scalable, and dynamic storage service offering. 
      The core storage system is designed to provide a safe, secure, automatically re-sizing 
      and network-accessible way to store data.
      You can store an unlimited quantity of files and each one can be as large as 5 gigabytes. 
      Users can store as much as
      they want and pay only for storage space they actually use.
    </para>
    <para>    
      Additionally, Cloud Files provides a simple yet powerful way to publish and distribute 
      content behind the industry-leading Akamai Content Distribution Network (CDN). Cloud Files users get access to this network automatically
      without having to worry about contracts, additional costs, or technical hurdles.
    </para>
    <para>
      Cloud Files allows users to store/retrieve files and CDN-enable content via a simple 
      ReST (Representational
      State Transfer) web service interface. 
      There are also language-specific APIs that utilize the ReST API to make it much
      easier for developers to integrate into their applications.
    </para>
    <para>
     For more details on the Cloud Files service, please refer to 
      <link xlink:href="http://www.rackspacecloud.com/cloud_hosting_products/files"
        >http://www.rackspacecloud.com/cloud_hosting_products/files</link>.
    </para>
  </chapter>
   <chapter xml:id="Ideal_Uses_of_Cloud_Files-d1e103">
     <title>Ideal Uses of Cloud Files</title>
     <para>
       There are a number of ideal uses for the Cloud Files service, such as:
       <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
           <para>Backing up or archiving data</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <para>Serving images/videos (streaming data to the user’s browser)</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <para>Serving content with a world-class CDN (Akamai)</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <para>Storing secondary/tertiary, or static web-accessible data</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <para>Developing new applications with data storage integration</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <para>Storing data when predicting storage capacity is difficult</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <para>Storing data for applications affordably</para>
         </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
     </para>
   </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="Why_Use_Cloud_Files-d1e159">
      <title>Why Use Cloud Files?</title>
      <para>
        There are a number of reasons to choose the Cloud Files service over similar services available in the market.
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Simplicity of security mechanisms and CDN functionality</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Affordability of the service </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Flexibility in terms, paying as you go</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Great performance</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>World-class support</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </chapter> 
    <chapter xml:id="Cloud_Files_Features-d1e201">
      <title>Cloud Files Features</title>
      <para>The key features of Cloud Files key 
        include <link linkend="Simplicity-d1e206">simplicity</link>,
        <link linkend="Affordability-d1e221">affordability</link>, <link
        linkend="Flexibility-d1e233">flexibility</link>, 
        <trademark class='registered'><link linkend="World-Class_Support-d1e248">Fanatical Support</link></trademark>, <link linkend="Data_Redundancy-d1e258">data redundancy</link>,
      and <link linkend="Security-d1e267">security</link>. </para>
      <section xml:id="Simplicity-d1e206">
        <title>Simplicity</title>
        <para>
          Cloud Files is simple to use for developers and non-developers alike. 
          Users can get started in as little as five minutes.
          Users do not have to know how to code to use Cloud Files and CDN. 
          Users need only sign up for Cloud
          Files, create a Container, upload a file and publish that Container’s content through 
          the CDN. 
          The Cloud Files GUI is easy to navigate and use. 
          The Rackspace browser-based control
          panel lets users easily upload files and distribute on a CDN without writing any code.
        </para>
        <para>
          All the content can be backed by a CDN without complex negotiations and details of updating content for optimizing
          delivery. 
          Given the complexity of the CDN, 
          users may have to make a series of choices such as number of servers
          to use, etc., before obtaining the service. 
          After making the choices, users must ensure that their usage bills are accurate. 
          All
          these issues are handled by Cloud Files. 
          CDNs have, in the past, been the prerogative of companies with more money
          but Cloud Files changes that.
        </para>
        <para> Cloud Files is a user-friendly and developer-friendly service. Security mechanisms
        are simple to use. Third-party tools which further simplify use of the storage service are
        available. Developers can use an Application Programming Interface (API) with
        language-specific bindings to develop utilities or applications. The API is easy to use and
        is documented with examples to get started quickly. </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="Affordability-d1e221">
        <title>Affordability</title>
        <para> Pricing for Cloud Files starts at </para>
      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>10 cents per gigabyte of storage per month</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>12 cents per gigabyte for CDN bandwidth – bandwidth
              from the edge location to the user</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>12 cents per gigabyte for outgoing bandwidth without
              CDN – bandwidth out from Cloud Files that is not on the
              CDN</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>There is no charge for inbound bandwidth and
        there are no per-requests fees for CDN. For the latest pricing
        information, please refer to Cloud Files and CDN at the
        following web site <link
          xlink:href="http://www.rackspace.com/cloud/public-pricing/"
          >http://www.rackspace.com/cloud/public-pricing/</link>. </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="Flexibility-d1e233">
        <title>Flexibility</title>
        <para>
          Cloud Files is a dynamically expanding storage system. 
          It is very flexible and is built on the pay-for-use principle. 
          Customers
          can use as much or little storage as necessary, while paying only for storage space used. 
          There is no limit on total space
          used and individual files can be as large as 5GB. 
          The GUI control panel allows users to check storage space used and
          bandwidth utilized. 
          There are no upfront fees or contracts and end users pay only for storage space used and outgoing
          bandwidth that they use.
        </para>
        <para> System administrators can use this for simple manual updates as well. Users do not
        have to know how to code to use Cloud Files and CDN. No API is required to share files.
        Non-developers have a simple web interface that can be used to quickly and easily upload
        data and enable CDN access. Multiple third party tools make it even more flexible for users
        of specific environments such as the Mac OS. </para>
        <para>
          Developers can use the ReST web service and language-specific APIs in 
          PHP, Python, Java, Ruby, and C#/.NET. 
          The APIs provide full support for managing content in Cloud Files and 
          publishing content over the CDN. 
          The API allows
          developers to work in the language they feel most comfortable using.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="World-Class_Support-d1e248">
        <title>World-Class Support</title>
        <para>
          With Cloud Files, world-class technical support is only a click away at no
          additional cost. 
          Live support, with real people, is available 24/7. 
          <trademark class='registered'>Fanatical Support</trademark> is built into the price. 
          Users can get peace of mind knowing that technical support is just a
          phone call or online chat away &#x2014; at any time of day.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="Data_Redundancy-d1e258">
        <title>Data Redundancy</title>
        <para> The Cloud Files storage system is designed to be highly available and fault tolerant.
        Cloud Files achieves client data redundancy by replicating three full copies on different
        storage nodes. Storage nodes are grouped in logical Zones within Rackspace datacenters.
        Zones are connected to redundant Internet backbone providers and reside on redundant power
        supplies and generators. The system has been engineered to be
        fully functional even in the event of a major service disruption within a datacenter.
        Content on the CDN provides an additional layer of data redundancy. </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="Security-d1e267">
        <title>Security</title>
        <para>
          Cloud Files uses a number of different measures to ensure that your data is kept safe. 
          First and foremost, all traffic
          between clients and the Cloud Files system uses SSL to establish a secure, 
          encrypted communication channel. 
          This ensures that any data (usernames, passwords, and content) 
          cannot be intercepted and read by a third-party. 
          Users authenticate with a valid username and API Access Key and are granted 
          a session authentication token. 
          These authentication
          tokens are used to validate all operations against Cloud Files. 
          While there is no way to terminate a valid session by the user, 
          session tokens automatically expire after 24 hours, 
          forcing clients to resend their credentials.
        </para>
        <para> The API Access Key is only available after login to the
        customer's Rackspace Cloud Control Panel. Users must enter
        their valid username and password to gain access to view the
        API Access Key or to generate a new key. </para>
        <para>
          It is important to note that Cloud Files does not apply any transformations 
          to data before storing it. 
          This means that
          Cloud Files does not store data in encrypted form unless the client encrypts it 
          prior to transmission. 
          This allows users
          to select the type and level of encryption best suited to their applications.
        </para>
        <para>
          When deleting storage Objects from the Cloud Files system, 
          all copies of data are permanently removed within a
          matter of minutes. 
          Furthermore, the physical blocks making up the customer's data are zeroed over 
          before that space is
          re-used for other customer data. 
          In other words, after a delete request, the data is unrecoverable.
        </para>
      </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="Tools_and_Applications_for_Cloud_Files-d1e286">
      <title>Tools and Applications for Cloud Files</title>
      <para>
        In addition to the ReST API and its language-specific bindings, 
        there are several other ways for users to interact with Cloud Files.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="Control_Panel-d1e294">
        <title>Cloud Control Panel</title>
        <para>The Rackspace Cloud Control Panel is one way to access
        Cloud Files. This tool provides a way to understand, at a high
        level, how Cloud Files works. It gives system administrators a
        view of the various containers and objects stored in Cloud
        Files. You can create containers in the Cloud Control Panel,
        and then upload, download, and delete files.  It also provides
        a means of updating individual files and the metadata that
        describes those files. <figure>
          <title>Rackspace Cloud Control Panel</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="svg" align="center" scale="50"
                fileref="figures/cf-screenshot-ControlPanel.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
        <para>Access this screen by logging in to your Cloud Control
          Panel at <link xlink:href="https://mycloud.rackspace.com">http://mycloud.rackspace.com</link>, and then clicking on
          <command>Files</command> (along the top) to view the Cloud
        Files page. </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="FireUploader_GUI-d1e314">
        <title>FireUploader GUI</title>
        <para> FireUploader is a tool from Suchi Software; it provides an intuitive interface to
        move and manage files in Cloud Files. It works as a plug-in to the Mozilla Firefox browser
        and provides a GUI to manage the movement as well as metadata in Cloud Files. While setting
        up the tool, you must supply your Rackspace Cloud username; when prompted for a password,
        enter your API Access Key. This tool provides a creative way of working with available Cloud
        Files features to allow users to simulate a hierarchical file system structure. For more
        information, please see the FireUploader web site at <link xlink:href="http://www.fireuploader.com">http://www.fireuploader.com</link>. 
          <figure>
            <title>FireUploader Interface to Cloud Files</title>
            <mediaobject >
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="svg" align="center" scale="50" fileref="figures/cf-screenshot-FireUploader.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
      </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="Cyberduck-d1e337">
        <title>Cyberduck</title>
        <para> Cyberduck is an open-source Cloud Files browser licensed under the GPL; it's
        available for Mac and Windows. Cyberduck features an easy-to-use interface with easily
        accessible bookmarks. The browser outline view allows users to browse large folder
        structures efficiently and preview files with Quick Look. Cyberduck also provides seamless
        integration with many external editors, making it easy to change content quickly. It
        provides a way to upload and configure Cloud Files to distribute content over the CDN. For
        more information, please see the Cyberduck web site at <link
          xlink:href="http://cyberduck.ch/">http://cyberduck.ch/</link>. 
          <figure>
            <title>Cyberduck Interface to Cloud Files</title>
            <mediaobject >
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="svg" align="center" scale="80" fileref="figures/cf-screenshot-Cyberduck.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
      </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="cloudStorageApp-d1e337">
      <title>Rackspace Cloud Storage App for Microsoft
        SharePoint</title>
      <para>Rackspace Cloud Storage App for Microsoft SharePoint
        enables you to work with files inside of Rackspace Cloud Files
        alongside SharePoint content. You can download the Cloud
        Storage App from the <link
          xlink:href="http://office.microsoft.com/en-us/store/rackspace-cloud-storage-app-for-microsoft-sharepoint-WA104094200.aspx?redir=0"
          >SharePoint Store</link>. Cloud Storage App reduces costs
        and frees valuable space on a SharePoint deployment's
        Microsoft SQL Server databases by storing data in your cloud
        account. The app also gives you the ability to expose Cloud
        Files containers and objects directly in SharePoint websites
        where you can download, upload, modify, and share files with
        others. With Cloud Storage App, you can perform the following
        tasks: </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Manage Cloud Files objects directly inside your
            SharePoint portal</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Add objects to Cloud File containers using a
            drag-and-drop user interface</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Delete objects from Cloud File containers one at a
            time or in bulk</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Collaborate with others, even users who do not have
            SharePoint credentials, by generating temporary URLs that
            expire after a certain number of days</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>For more information about the Rackspace Cloud Storage App
        for Microsoft SharePoint, see <link
          xlink:href="http://www.rackspace.com/knowledge_center/article/cloud-storage-app-for-microsoft-sharepoint-overview"
          >http://www.rackspace.com/knowledge_center/article/cloud-storage-app-for-microsoft-sharepoint-overview</link>. </para>
    </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="Developing_Applications_for_Cloud_Files-d1e361">
      <title>Developing Applications for Cloud Files</title>
      <para>
        There are several programming interfaces for using Cloud Files 
        that allow developers to integrate the storage
        solution into new applications or provide automated ways of accessing the system. 
      </para>
      <section xml:id="ReST_API-d1e369">
        <title>ReST API</title>
        <para>
          Cloud Files allows users to store/retrieve files via a simple 
          Web Service (ReST: Representational State Transfer) interface. 
          New Cloud Files storage applications such as the tools described in the previous sections 
          can be designed
          and developed by using the ReST application programming interface. 
          For more details on developing Cloud Files applications, please refer to the 
          Rackspace Cloud Files API Developer Guide at 
          <link xlink:href="http://docs.rackspacecloud.com/files/api/cf-devguide-latest.pdf"
            >http://docs.rackspacecloud.com/files/api/cf-devguide-latest.pdf</link>.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="Language-Specific_API_Bindings-d1e381">
        <title>Language-Specific API Bindings</title>
        <para> In addition to the ReST API, there are
        language-specific API documents and assets for C#/.NET,
        Python, PHP, Java and Ruby. These developer resources are
        documented on the API Documentation web site at <link
          xlink:href="http://docs.rackspace.com/sdks/guide/content/index.html"
          >http://docs.rackspace.com/sdks/guide/content/index.html</link>. </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="Caveats-d1e393">
        <title>Caveats</title>
        <para>
          There are many advantages to a storage system like Cloud Files and many appropriate use-cases. 
          However, there are some limitations
          and some use-cases for which Cloud Files is not an ideal storage solution. 
          Keep the following
          in mind as you further explore Cloud Files:
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Native support within your operating system. 
                It is not possible to “mount” or “map” the Cloud Files storage
                system as a virtual hard-disk on your computer or server.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Disk mirroring or backup solutions that require byte/block level differences. 
                There are no concepts of “appending data” or 
                “file locking” operations within Cloud Files.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Data may be organized into storage compartments called “Containers”, 
                but Containers cannot be nested. 
                Since there is only one top level of organization, 
                you are not able to upload nested directory/folder structures
                into Cloud Files unless a transformation is performed to flatten the structure.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                There is no built-in concept of permissions or access controls in 
                Cloud Files such as you may be accustomed 
                to in a traditional file system.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                There are no transcoding capabilities to read a file in one format 
                and upload it in one or more other formats
                into Cloud Files.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para>
      </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="Additional_Resources-d1e436">
      <title>Additional Resources</title>
      <para>
        The official support channels 
        (phone, chat, email, forums, and knowledge base articles) for Cloud Files are available
        through the Rackspace Cloud web site at 
        <link xlink:href="http://www.rackspacecloud.com"
          >http://www.rackspacecloud.com</link>.
      </para>
      <para>
        The system status page at 
        <link xlink:href="http://status.rackspacecloud.com/cloudfiles/"
          >http://status.rackspacecloud.com/cloudfiles/</link>        
        can be reviewed
        if you believe the Cloud Files system is not functioning to your expectations. 
        This page is updated to reflect up-to-date information
        about the system’s current health and status.
      </para>
      <para>
        Interested users can also follow updates/announcements via twitter at 
        <link xlink:href="http://www.twitter.com/rackspace"
          >http://www.twitter.com/rackspace</link>.
      </para>
      <para>
        Developers are also encouraged to join some of the members of the Cloud Files team at 
        irc.freenode.net on
        the #cloudfiles channel. 
        This is not an official Cloud Files support channel but should rather be viewed as a community
        meeting place to share ideas and discuss Cloud Files.
      </para>
    </chapter>      
 </book>
